Guide to the Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies records, 1966-2014 RL.11552
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Center Offices, 1969-2013
  - Office of Communications and Marketing (OCM), 1969-2013
    - OCM Media, 1980-2012
      - OCM Computer files, 1972-2011
        - ALI files, undated (Box 39, Disk RL11552-OP-0170)
        - Annual Report materials, 2005 (Box 39, Disk RL11552-OP-0172)
        - Barcode, undated (Box 39, Disk RL11552-OP-0182)
        - Healthcare Summit, 2009 Sep 17 (Box 39, Disk RL11552-OP-0183)
        - Project 2010 (client) (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0338)
        - Annual Report materials, 2010 (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0340)
        - Place Matters conference fact sheets and presentations, 2011 Sep 7 (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0341)
        - Health Policy Logo, 2004 (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0343)
        - NOBCO Membership List, 2009-2010 (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0344)
        - VA/NB Alliance, 2007 (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0356)
        - The Economic Impacts of HIV/AIDS documents, 2003 Mar 5 (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0384)
        - Public Policies and Practices in Child Welfare Systems by Jones, Ernestine F. paper, 2006 (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0385)
        - Julia Nixon pdfs, 2007 (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0386)
        - Nutrition publication fonts and formatting, 2007 (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0387)
        - Global Village publication fonts and formatting, 2007 (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0388)
        - Infant publication fonts and formatting, 2004; 2007 (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0389)
        - FOCUS magazine graphics, 2002-2007; 6 items (Box 40, Disk RL11552-OP-0390 - RL11552-OP-0395)
- Center Institutes, 1975-2012
  Partnering with funders, the Joint Center hosted institutes of specialized interest. The series includes administrative materials, working papers, final reports, electronic records, audiovisual media, and photographs from the National Policy Institute (NPI), the Civic Engagement and Governance Institute (CEGI), and the Institute for Responsible Fatherhood (IRF).
  - National Policy Institute (NPI), 1975-2011
    The National Policy Institute (NPI) was held every four years at the beginning each presidential election year for groups representing black public officials from federal, state and local government organizations to present policy and work on issues of importance to African American communities. Later NPI became an independent program named the National Policy Alliance. This subseries includes programs, essays, special reports, fact sheets, financial reports, memorandums, correspondence, financial summaries, proposals, mailings, personnel rosters, steering committee documents, registration information, newsletters, budgets, projects, event planning materials, research, articles, surveys, agendas, lists of program participants, and photographs related to the event. The materials are arranged chronologically.
    - Third National Policy Institute photographs, 1970s (Box 127)
      Includes images of Eddie Williams.
    - Third through Fifth National Policy Institute, 1975; 1983-1985; 1986-1987; 42 folders (Box 150)
    - Fourth National Policy Institute photographs, 1984 (Box 127)
    - Fourth National Policy Institute, graphics, 1984 (Box 184)
    - Fourth National Policy Institute, audiocassette sessions A, B, C, D, EA, EB, FA, FB, G, and no. 1-20, 1984 Mar 1-2 (Box 171, Audio-cassette RL11552-CS-0051 - RL11552-CS-0079)
      This subseries includes panels, addresses and speeches from the Fourth NPI arranged numerically. Speakers include Charlotte Collins, Bailus Walker, Margaret Simms, Elliott Skinner, Yvonne, Scruggs, Frederic Leigh, Ron Tallon, Eddie Williams, Sullivan Robinson, Arnold Tompkins, William Jefferson, Franklin Raines, William Winter, David Bostis, Karen Scott Collins, Arnold Epstein, Sylvia Drew Ivie, and Bill Clinton.
    - Fourth National Policy Institute, videotapes 1-7, 1984 Mar 1-2; 7 items (Box 167, Video-cassette RL11552-Umatic-0017 - RL11552-Umatic-0023)
      morning panel with K. Hall, W. Felder, D. Ridings, R. Yzaguirre.
    - Fifth National Policy Institute, 1987; 59 folders (Box 151)
    - Fifth National Policy Institute and dinner contacts photographs, 1987 (Box 127)
      Includes images of Colin Powell, Eddie Williams, Joyce London Alexander, and Bob Washington.
    - Fifth National Policy Institute and Powell dinner photograph negatives, 1988 (Box 127)
      Includes images of Marion Barry, and Maynard Jackson.
    - Fifth National Policy Institute and Powell dinner photographs, 1988 (Box 127)
    - Fifth National Policy Institute photography contact sheets, 1988 (Box 127)
    - Fifth National Policy Institute photograph negatives, 1988 (Box 127)
    - Fifth National Policy Institute photographs, 1988 (Box 127)
      Includes images of Basil Patterson, Dean Jones (of Howard University), and Herbert O. Reid
    - Fifth NPI, Making Democracy Work, audiocassette, 1988 (Box 172, Audio-cassette RL11552-CS-0112)
    - Fifth NPI, audiocassette sessions no. 1-25, 1988 Jan 20-23; 32 items (Box 172, Audio-cassette RL11552-CS-0080 - RL11552-CS-0111)
      This subseries includes panels, addresses and speeches from the Fifth NPI. Speakers include Dr. Vivian Penn, Roger Wilkins, Eddie Williams, Dr. Sullivan, Jesse Jackson, Richard Nixon, and Gerald Ford.
    - Sixth National Policy Institute, 1988-1992; 55 folders (Box 152)
    - Group Sensitivities project, 1989 (Box 153)
    - National Policy Institute newsletter correspondence, 1989 (Box 153)
    - National Council of La Raza, 1990 (Box 153)
    - National Policy Institute Steering committee meeting photographs, 1990 Mar 14 (Box 127)
    - Union Institute, 1990 Jun 20 (Box 153)
    - Georgetown University, 1990 Jul 31 (Box 153)
    - AARP, 1991 (Box 153)
    - Urban Policy Institutes, 1991 (Box 153)
    - African American Action Alert Communication network, 1991 Mar 19 (Box 153)
    - National American Indian Council, 1991 May 24 (Box 153)
    - Sixth through Seventh National Policy Institute, 1991-1992; 1996; 2000; 27 folders (Box 153)
    - Sixth National NPI photographs, 1992 (Box 185)
      Includes images of Russell E. Owens, Sharon Pratt Kelly, Ronald Brown, Thelma Wyatt Cummings, Jesse Jackson, and Eleanor Farrar on scrapbook pages.
    - Sixth National Policy Institute photographs, 1992 Jan 23-25 (Box 127)
      Includes images of Eddie Williams, and Jesse Jackson.
    - Sixth National Policy Institute program photographs, 1992 (Box 127)
    - National Policy Institute Steering committee meeting and Health committee meeting photographs, 1995 (Box 127)
      Includes images of George Evans, Donna Crews, Dorothy Jackson, Davide Moore, Shep Wilbun, Earline Parmon, and Joyce London Alexander.
    - Seventh National Policy Institute press briefing photographs, 1996 Jan (Box 127)
    - Seventh National Policy Institute photographs, 1996 Jan 25-27; 6 folders (Box 127, Box 128)
    - Eighth National Policy Institute Salute to Appointed and Elected Officials, 2000 Jan 20 (Box 128)
    - National Policy Institute Globalization, Education, and Technology forum, 2000 Jan 21 (Box 128)
      Includes images of Earl C. Rickman, Col. Jerry A. Oliver, and Eddie Williams.
    - National Policy Alliance, 2007-2011; 13 folders (Box 153)
  - Civic Engagement and Governance Institute (CEGI), 1981-2012, undated
    The mission of the Civic Engagement and Governance Institute (CEGI) was to understand how people of color perceive the world and to increase their participation in democratic institutions. To meet this goal, CEGI issued publications and sponsored events where topics included children's and adolescent health, HIV/AIDS, African Americans and climate change, Social Security, Medicaid, Latino reproductive health, and various community-based projects. Major funders included the Ford Foundation and the Annie E. Casey Foundation. This subseries is arranged chronologically.
    - Devolution data, undated (Box 157)
    - Leigh, Wilhelmina - Soft Skills, undated (Box 157)
    - Publication notes and correspondence, 1981-1985 (Box 157)
    - Black Elected Officials, 1986; 1993-1999 (Box 157)
    - Health Assessment, 1987-1992 (Box 157)
    - Beyond Affirmative Action, 1989-1991 (Box 157)
    - Poverty, Inequality, and the Crisis of Social Policy, 1991 (Box 157)
    - Research and Policy, roundtable, 1993 (Box 157)
    - Health and Policy, roundtable, 1993 Jun 10 (Box 157)
      Roundtable and forums include itineraries, working papers, correspondence, and other documents related to the event. Each folder has been labeled and dated according to the date of the forum or meeting, although the dates of other supporting documents that accompany those materials may vary.
    - Racial Differences in Home Ownership Rates, 1994-2008; undated (Box 157)
    - Health Care Needs of Hispanics and African Americans, dinner, 1994 May 25 (Box 157)
    - In the Nation's Interest, forum, 1995 Sep 18 (Box 157)
    - HIV/AIDS and African American Youth, forum, 1995 Jun 29 (Box 157)
    - Health Policy Advisory Committee, meeting, 1995 Dec 6 (Box 157)
    - Labor markets, report, 1996 (Box 157)
    - Data Book on the Health of Women of Color, correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 157)
    - Health Issues for African American Youth, forum, 1996 Feb 12 (Box 157)
    - HIV/AIDS Among African American Youth, forum, 1996 Mar 9 (Box 157)
    - Economic Policy Forum on Job Creation within Health Industries, 1996 Nov 20 (Box 157)
    - Leigh, Wilhelmina - State-by-State Worker Training, 1997 Jun 23; 2 folders (Box 157)
    - HIV/AIDS in African-American Youth in North Carolina, forum, 1997 Oct 3 (Box 157)
    - The Future of Public Hospitals, 1997 Oct 15 (Box 157)
    - One Year After Welfare Reform Implementation, forum, 1997 Nov 12 (Box 157)
    - Chaulk Project, Seattle, 1998-1999 (Box 157)
    - Teen Pregnancy Prevention, 1998-1999 (Box 157)
    - Annie E. Casey Foundation, jobs initiative, 1998 Aug 6-7 (Box 157)
    - Race and Work Readiness, meeting, 1998 Aug 6-7 (Box 157)
    - Knight Foundation, 1999 (Box 157)
    - Neighborhood-Based Health Interventions and Community Economic Development, 1999 (Box 157)
    - HIV/AIDS Prevention Education Project, forum, 1999 Feb 19 (Box 157)
    - Skills Development for Black Workers, forum, 1999 Nov 3 (Box 157)
    - Reproductive Health, advisory workgroup meeting, 2000 (Box 157)
    - Teen Pregnancy Prevention, 2000 (Box 157)
    - Health Care and Neighborhood Transformation, C. Patrick Chaulk reports, 2000-2003; 2 folders (Box 157)
    - Survey on Black Elected Officials on HIV/AIDS, 2000 Jan (Box 157)
    - Mobilizing to Fight HIV/AIDS in the African American Community, forum, 2000 Jan 20; 2 folders (Box 157)
    - Adolescent Health, funding, 2001; 2 folders (Box 157)
    - Driskoll, Anne K. - Adolescent Latino Reproductive Health, 2001 (Box 157)
    - Annie E. Casey Foundation, funding, 2002-2006; 3 folders (Box 157)
    - Leigh, Wilhelmina - Public Views about Devolution, 2002 Jun (Box 157)
    - Leigh, Wilhelmina - Devolution Poll Report, 2002 Jun 20 (Box 157)
    - Adolescent Reproductive Health, 2003 (Box 157)
    - Accessibility and Usability of Census Data for Community-Based Organizations, forum, 2003 Jul 25 (Box 157)
    - Workforce Development Health Project, 2004 (Box 157)
    - Disparities in Adolescent Reproductive and Sexual Health, 2005 (Box 158)
    - Wilhelmina, Leigh - Health Care and Medicaid Program, 2005 (Box 158)
    - Medicare survey, 2005 (Box 158)
    - Social Security, Ford proposal, 2005-2007 (Box 158)
    - Advisory Committee on Climate Change, 2005-2008 (Box 158)
      Committee documents include newsletters, summaries of goals and research, correspondence, and scholarly papers.
    - Freddie Mac, funded research, 2006-2008 (Box 158)
    - National Poll of African American Opinions on Social Security, closed media briefing, 2006 Jun 27 (Box 158)
    - Meeting of Social Security Dissemination Partners, 2006 Mar 29 (Box 158)
    - African Americans and Social Security Disability Insurance, 2007 (Box 158)
    - Ford Asset Building, 2007 (Box 158)
    - Ford, original documents, 2007; 2009-2010; 2 folders (Box 158)
    - Freddie Mac, funded project, 2007-2010 (Box 158)
    - Advisory Group meeting, asset building, 2007 Oct 23 (Box 158)
    - Carr, James H. - In the Wake of Katrina, 2008 (Box 158)
    - Child health Disparities, 2008 (Box 158)
    - Disparities in Health Indicators for Children and Youth of Color, 2008 (Box 158)
    - Leigh-Trader, Karyn - Understanding the Role of African American Churches, 2008 (Box 158)
    - Morse, Reilly - Environmental Justice through the Eye of Hurricane Katrina, 2008 (Box 158)
      Publications are housed in their own individual folders. Accompanying documentation and correspondence related to each publication have also been included, where relevant.
    - Wenger, Michael R. - No More Katrinas, 2008 (Box 158)
    - Child Health Disparities, products, 2008-2009 (Box 158)
    - Closing the Wealth Gap, agreement, 2008-2009 (Box 158)
    - Ford Asset Building, calls, 2008-2009 (Box 158)
    - Ford, year two work, 2008-2009 (Box 158)
    - Commission to Engage African Americans on Climate Change, 2008 Jul 29 (Box 158)
    - Civic Engagement and Governance Institute, dinner and planning forum, 2008 Oct 1-2 (Box 158)
    - Asset Building in Low-Income Communities of Color, 2009 (Box 158)
    - Child Health Briefs, 2009 (Box 158)
    - Copenhagen, meetings, 2009 (Box 158)
    - Multicultural Sustainability Summits, 2009 (Box 158)
    - State Asset Building Project, 2009 (Box 158)
    - Press contacts, 2009; undated (Box 158)
    - Commission to Engage African Americans on Climate Change, town hall, 2009 Jun 17 (Box 158)
    - National Policy Forum, 2009 Jun 29 (Box 158)
    - Creating Economically Inclusive Communities, 2009 Sep 23 (Box 158)
    - African Americans on Climate Change and Conservation, 2009 Sep 30 (Box 158)
    - United Nations Climate Change Conference, 2009 Nov 13 (Box 158)
    - American Association of Retired Persons and Social Security, 2010 (Box 158)
    - Fenton Communications, 2010 (Box 158)
    - Focus on Health Reform, 2010 (Box 158)
    - U.S. Forest Service, proposal, 2010 (Box 158)
    - Kellogg Foundation Funding, correspondence, 2010-2012 (Box 158)
    - Commission to Engage African Americans on Climate Change, fact sheets, 2010; undated (Box 158)
    - Commission to Engage African Americans on Climate Change, town hall, planning retreat, 2010 Mar 9 (Box 158)
    - National Academy of Social Insurance, 2011 (Box 158)
    - Wilhelmina, Leigh - Feeding America, 2011 (Box 158)
    - Capital Area Asset Builders, correspondence, 2011-2012 (Box 158)
    - National Association of Real Estate Brokers, 2011-2012 (Box 158)
    - National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities, 2012 (Box 158)
  - Institute for Responsible Fatherhood (IRF), 1993-1997
    Materials include correspondence, budgets, planning and programming documents related to Fathers and Children Eliminating Domestic Violence (FACE), and the IRF project formed by Charles Ballard, funded by the Ford Foundation and administered by the Joint Center, and is arranged chronologically.
    - Personnel Handbook and Guide, 1993 Apr (Box 159)
    - Budgets, 1994 Oct-1996 Dec (Box 159)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 159)
    - Funding, 1994 (Box 159)
    - Nations Bank, account, 1994-1995 (Box 159)
    - Planning, 1994 (Box 159)
    - Proposal and notes, 1994-1995 (Box 159)
    - Site Planning, 1994-1995 (Box 159)
    - Ford Foundation Grant, 1995 (Box 159)
    - Audit, 1995 Dec-1996 Nov (Box 159)
    - Correspondence, 1995 Jan-Jun; 3 folders (Box 159)
    - Correspondence, 1995 Aug-Sep; 2 folders (Box 159)
    - Cost proposal, 1995 Sep 5 (Box 159)
    - Fundraising and public relations, 1995 Sep 14 (Box 159)
    - Office space, 1995 Oct-1996 May (Box 159)
    - Planning, 1995 (Box 159)
    - Staffing, 1995 Dec (Box 159)
    - Strategic Plan, draft, 1995 Sep-Oct (Box 159)
    - Strategic Planning, 1995 Dec (Box 159)
    - Correspondence, 1996 Jan (Box 159)
    - Correspondence, 1996 Mar-Aug; 2 folders (Box 159)
    - Employment manual, 1996 May 28 (Box 159)
    - Fathers and Children Eliminating Domestic Violence (FACE), 1996 (Box 159)
    - Final Report, 1996 May 23 (Box 159)
    - Ford Foundation Correspondence, 1996 (Box 159)
    - Funding and Development, 1996 Feb (Box 159)
    - Funding, 1996 Mar-Apr; 2 folders (Box 159)
    - Meetings, 1996 Mar (Box 159)
    - Newsbriefs, 1996 Jan-Feb (Box 159)
    - Proposal, 1996 Mar-May; 3 folders (Box 159)
    - Strategic Planning, 1996 (Box 159)
    - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 159)
    - Communications plan, 1996-1996 (Box 159)
    - Development and fundraising plan, 1996-1997 (Box 159)
    - Employee manual, 1996-1998 (Box 159)
    - Financial management manual, 1996-1999 (Box 159)
    - Financial management plan, 1996-2000 (Box 159)
    - Program manual, 1996-2001 (Box 159)
    - Program replication plan, 1996-2002 (Box 159)
    - Position descriptions, 1996-2003 (Box 159)
    - Turning the Hearts of Fathers, 1996-2004 (Box 159)
- Electronic Records, 1980-2013; 6.9 Megabytes 1237 files; 18 floppy disks with 1231 files; 6 video files (3 .mp4, 3 .mov)
  Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library reading room. To request access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these records.
  The original computer disks acquired with the records of the Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies (JCPES) contain files of many types, chiefly software programs, memos, correspondence, events materials, analytical summaries of panels and meetings on a wide variety of social issues, and administrative materials such as budgets. These files have been migrated to a library server. The three video files all relate to the JCPES annual Gala Dinner event in 2013; for ease of access, .mp4 video files have been made available as use copies; access to original .mov files is availalable upon request.
  - Floppy disk 1, 1992; 1.2 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 2 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0001)
    Box Label: "Meeting Trak Backup Disks"
  - Floppy disk 2, 1992; .897 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 2 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0002)
  - Floppy disk 3, 1988-1992; .304 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 23 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0003)
    Box Label: "Backup of Wordperfect Files from Leading Edge Computer / Disks 1-10 SNPI ??"
  - Floppy disk 4, 1987-1992; .301 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 86 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0004)
  - Floppy disk 5, 1986-1992; .299 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 75 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0005)
  - Floppy disk 6, 1987-1992; .343 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 107 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0006)
  - Floppy disk 7, 1987-1992; .303 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 102 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0007)
  - Floppy disk 8, 1987-1992; .300 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 98 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0008)
  - Floppy disk 9, 1980-1992; .301 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 107 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0009)
  - Floppy disk 10, 1987-1992; .293 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 97 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0010)
  - Floppy disk 11, 1987-1992; .327 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 28 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0011)
  - Floppy disk 12, 1987-1992; .309 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 88 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0012)
    Box Label: "Backup of Wordperfect Files from Leading Edge Computer / Meeting-Track Backup for SNPI"
  - Floppy disk 13, 1986-1992; .324 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 64 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0013)
  - Floppy disk 14, 1980-1992; .321 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 70 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0014)
  - Floppy disk 15, 1987-1992; .334 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 39 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0015)
  - Floppy disk 16, 1988-1992; .290 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 55 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0016)
  - Floppy disk 17, 1986-1992; .307 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 92 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0017)
  - Floppy disk 18, 1988-1992; .181 Megabytes 1 5.25" floppy disk; 1 5.25" floppy disk with 75 files (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0001, Disk RL11552-FL5-0018)
  - Bravo JCPES Gala 2013 MP4 Videos, 1.3 Gigabytes 3 .mp4 files; 3 video files (.mp4) (Digital-materials RL11552-SET-0002)
    These files are intended as access copies with content duplicating that of the original video files in .mov format. Original .mov video files are available upon request. The 2013 Annual Gala video chiefly focuses on the program speakers. Joe Biden, U.S. Vice President, gives a lengthy speech. Other speakers include JCPES Board Chair Cynthia Marshall, members of the Congressional Black Caucus, and Susan Rice, U.N. Ambassador.